<partintro>  <title>Random Introduction</title>

  <sidebar>    <title>Overview</title>
 
    <para>First, a few thoughts on random number generation. It's hard
      to do right! The root cause, of course, is that computer
      algorithms themselves are not truly random. (Hence this library
      contains pseudo-random generators only.)

      There are many problems in implementing algorithms correctly and
      efficiently, and in coming up with good tests for generators and
      distributions. The history of pseudorandom number generation in
      simulation work is mostly embarrassing. This library attempts to
      do a decent job of generating random numbers, as well as
      documenting how things work and what shortcomings there are.

      If you want to learn more about random number generation, the
      bibliography in the &userbook-randomapp; contained in the
      &userbook; has useful notes.  Knuth is the main reference in
      this realm, but too old to describe most of the particular
      generators used here, many of which are drawn from recent
      literature.
    </para>

  </sidebar>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Random Dependencies" id="SWARM.RANDOM.SGML.SECT1.DEPEND">        <title>Dependencies</title> 

    <para>Following are the other header files imported by
    random.h:</para>

<programlisting>
#import &lt;objectbase.h&gt;
#import &lt;random/generators.h&gt;
#import &lt;random/distributions.h&gt;
#import &lt;random/randomdefs.h&gt;
#import &lt;random/randomvars.h&gt;</programlisting>


    <para>The <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> library interface is
      included to provide the basic object
      support. <filename>randomdefs.h</filename> contains some C
      preprocessor macros and typedefs used in the library.</para>

    <para>This reference guide contains the object definitions
      for generators and distributions (see the list above) 
      and also encodes the
      inheritance structure through the "Protocols that this protocol
      uses" section of each protocol. 

      Just click on a (sub-)protocol name to see what methods it
      implements. (You may want to review the section on Protocols in
      the Objective-C book here!)

    </para>

    <para>In the protocols described, any protocol that ultimately
      inherits from CREATABLE defines an object that you can use in
      your program. (This is part of the Swarm defobj machinery.) In
      other words, while 'InternalState' is a normal protocol (a list
      of method definitions), the name `ACGgen' refers to both a
      protocol and a class that implements that protocol. Similarly, 
      'GammaDist' defines both a protocol and a class that implements 
      that protocol.</para>

    <para>All generators and distributions ultimately inherit from
      SwarmObject.</para>
      
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Random Compatibility" id="SWARM.RANDOM.SGML.SECT1.COMPAT">        <title>Compatibility</title>

    <itemizedlist>      <listitem>        
        <formalpara>          <title>1.0.2 - 1.0.3</title>
          
          <para><emphasis>Note:</emphasis> The new random library does
            not work in the same way as the old one. This means that
            some applications that used the random library provided
            with the 1.0.2 release will be
            <emphasis>broken</emphasis>.  However, porting these
            applications to the new random library will be fairly easy
            since large efforts were made to adhere to the standard
            set with the last version and some backwards compatibility
            hooks were incorporated.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>        
        <formalpara>          <title>1.0, 1.1, 1.2, 1.3, 1.3.1, 1.4</title>
          
          <para>There were no major compatibility issues in these
            releases.

          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Random Usage Guide" id="SWARM.RANDOM.SGML.SECT1.USAGE">        <title>Usage Guide</title>
    
    <sect2>      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>random</emphasis> library contains two kinds
        of objects, the <emphasis>generators</emphasis> which implement
        different pseudo-random-number algorithms, and the 
        <emphasis>distributions</emphasis> which transform the (uniform)
        output from the generators into the desired simulated statistical
        distributions. (The Swarm random library does not 
        implement any <emphasis>true</emphasis> random number generators 
        at this time.)
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>      <title>Usage Guide for Beginners, Advanced Usage Guide and
        Guide to Generators and Distributions</title>
       
      <para>All these sections have been relocated to the
         in the new </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Random Subclassing Reference" id="SWARM.RANDOM.SGML.SECT1.SUBCLASS">        <title>Subclassing Reference</title>

    <para>Random library objects do not do anything exotic during the
      create phase. The competent programmer may subclass these objects
      in the normal manner.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Random Implementation Notes" id="SWARM.RANDOM.SGML.SECT1.IMPL">        <title>Implementation Notes</title>

    <para>This section provides implementation details for the current
      version of the random library.
    </para>

     &README.Random-0.8.xml;
     &README.Generators-0.8.xml;
     &README.Distributions-0.8.xml;

    <sect2>      <title>Programming yet to do</title>

      <para>Like many Open Source projects, this random-number library
        is a work in process. Further developments still on the to-do
        list are detailed below.
      </para>
      
            &Whats-Left-ToDo-0.8.xml;

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</partintro>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document:("randomcont.xml" "partintro")
end:
-->
