<webpage navto="yes" id="community-mailing-lists" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html40">
  <config class="html" param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2003-05-16 19:58:08 $"/>
 <config class="html" param="author" value="$Author: mgd $"/>
 <head>
  <title>Mailing lists</title>
  <abstract>
   <para>Subscribe to or review the Swarm mailing lists.</para>
  </abstract>
 </head>
 
 <note>
  <title>Mailing lists are now hosted on swarm.org</title> 
  
  <para>To subscribe, unsubscribe and general list information,
   please visit <ulink
    url="mailman/listinfo/">http://www.swarm.org/mailman/listinfo/</ulink> 
   and choose the list you are interested in.  <emphasis>Please, do
    not send subscription requests to the list, itself!!</emphasis>
  </para>
  
 </note>

 <caution>
  <title>You must be subscribed in order to post to lists</title>

  <para>To reduce spam, we've switched to subscriber-only posting.
   Non-members are <emphasis>not</emphasis> allowed to post messages
   to these list.  If you wish to just be able to post without
   approval, you can subscribe and then immediately select the
   "Disable delivery" option. This means you will be able to post to
   the list in future without waiting for the list administrator to
   manually approve each post, but you won't actually receive postings
   to the list (unless you want to).  You also <emphasis
    role="strong">must</emphasis> ensure that you post from an address
   that matches the address you are subscribed with.</para>

 </caution>

 <warning>
  <title>No HTML mail, please!</title>
  <para>Please send your mail in plain ASCII text, rather than HTML,
   it reduces bandwidth, is more portable (e.g. can be read under
   text-only mail clients like "pine") and saves space in our mailing
   list archives.  Also please refrain from posting attachments,
   unless absolutely necessary.  Provide a link to a web or ftp site
   if you wish to make available a download (e.g. a tar file, PDF
   etc.)</para>

 </warning>
 
 <simplesect id="mailing-list-announce">
  <title><ulink url="http://www.swarm.org/mailman/listinfo/announce">Announcements</ulink>: <literal
    moreinfo="none">announce@swarm.org</literal> (<ulink
    url="pipermail/announce/">archives</ulink>)</title>
  
  <para>The Swarm Announce list: <literal
    moreinfo="none">announce@swarm.org</literal>, is the list for
   people interested in Swarm to keep in touch with progress on the
   system. Major announcements of milestones and miscellaneous
   information about Swarm are posted here. <emphasis>Please do not
    mail to announce yourself.</emphasis>
  </para>

  </simplesect>
 <simplesect id="mailing-list-support">
  
  <title><ulink url="http://www.swarm.org/mailman/listinfo/support">Swarm Support</ulink>:
   <literal>support@swarm.org</literal> (<ulink url="pipermail/support">archives</ulink>) </title>
  
  <para> The Swarm Support list, <literal>support@swarm.org</literal>,
   is for the discussion of the technical details of the day to day
   usage of Swarm.  <literal>support</literal> is our major focus for
   user community. The traffic on this list can sometimes be quite
   technical. <literal>support</literal> is a sub-list of
   <literal>announce</literal>, which means that any message being
   sent to the <literal>announce</literal> list will also be sent to
   the <literal>support</literal> list. So, if you're interested in
   all the details and in the announcements, then simply subscribe to
   the <literal>support</literal> list. <emphasis>You do not need to
    subscribe to both lists.</emphasis> If you just want the
   announcements but don't care about the details, then subscribe to
   <literal>announce</literal>.</para>
  
 </simplesect>

 <simplesect id="mailing-list-modelling">
  <title><ulink url="http://www.swarm.org/mailman/listinfo/modelling">Swarm Modelling</ulink>:
   <literal>modelling@swarm.org</literal>  (<ulink
    url="pipermail/modelling/">archives</ulink>)</title>

  <para>The Swarm Modelling
   list,<literal>modelling@swarm.org</literal>, is for discussion of
   general modelling and simulation issues, particularly those having
   to do with Swarm or Agent Based Modelling (ABM).</para>

 </simplesect>
 
 <simplesect id="mailing-list-gis">
  
  <title><ulink url="http://www.swarm.org/mailman/listinfo/gis">Swarm
   &amp; GIS:</ulink>
   <literal>gis@swarm.org</literal> (<ulink
    url="pipermail/gis/">archives</ulink>)</title>
  
  <para>The Swarm GIS list,
   <literal>gis@swarm.org</literal>, is for discussion of
   Geographical Information Systems (GIS) like GRASS, particularly
   with respect to their usage in conjunction with Swarm.</para>

 </simplesect>

 <simplesect>
  <title>Search Swarm mailing lists via Google</title>

  <para>We currently have no dedicated search engine for the website
   or mailing lists, but we provide this customized search form which
   searches the Swarm website (including the mailing lists) via <ulink
    url="http://www.google.com/">Google</ulink>.  Just enter your
   keywords and click "Google Search":
  </para>

  <html:form action="http://www.google.com/search">

   <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
	 <inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	   <imagedata
	    fileref="http://www.google.com/logos/Logo_40wht.gif"
	    width="115" depth="45" align="center"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	   <phrase>Google</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	 </inlinemediaobject>
       </entry>
       <entry>
	<html:input type="text" name="q" size="25" maxlength="255" value=""/>
	<html:input type="hidden" name="q" size="25" maxlength="255"
	 value="site:www.swarm.org"/>
	<html:input type="submit" name="sa" value="Google Search"/>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
  </html:form>

  <para>(To search our site directly from Google, you can simply enter
   <literal>site:www.swarm.org</literal> followed by your keywords.
   e.g. to search for Debian, simply enter:
   <literal>site:www.swarm.org debian</literal>)</para>

 </simplesect>


</webpage>

<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document:("website.xml" "webpage")
End:
-->

