<webpage navto="yes" id="examples-mousetrap">
  <config class="html" param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2003-05-16 19:58:12 $"/>
  <config class="html" param="author" value="$Author: mgd $"/>
  <head>
    <title>Mousetrap</title>
    <abstract>
      <para><graphic fileref="graphics/mousetrap-world3.png"/>A simple discrete event simulation of fission.</para>
    </abstract>
  </head>

  <para>An old grade school demonstration of nuclear fission. Lay a
    bunch of mousetraps on the floor in a regular grid, and load each
    mousetrap with two ping pong balls. Drop one ping pong ball in
    the middle and watch the fun begin! (Unfortunately, Swarm does
    not yet support sound.)</para>
  
  <para>We implemented this in Swarm as an example of a simple
    discrete event simulation. Time stepping each mousetrap would be
    incredibly inefficient, since most mousetraps are doing nothing
    most of the time. Instead, we simulate each ping-pong ball as an
    event on the schedule. This method is much more efficient: you
    only compute when there is something to be done. One power of
    Swarm is that it supports both discrete event and time stepped
    models.</para>
  
  

  <para>
    <figure float="1">
      <title>Time evolution of the world</title>
      <literallayout format="linespecific" class="normal">
        <inlinegraphic fileref="graphics/mousetrap-world1.png"/> <inlinegraphic fileref="graphics/mousetrap-world2.png"/> <inlinegraphic fileref="graphics/mousetrap-world3.png"/> <inlinegraphic fileref="graphics/mousetrap-world4.png"/> </literallayout>
      
    </figure>
    
    These are snapshots of the world over time (from early on through
    the end of the reaction). Mousetraps change from blue to red when
    the trap fires. Each time a mousetrap is triggered, it schedules
    two trigger events for two random nearby mousetraps sometime in the
    near future. The balls only fly a limited distance; that induces a
    spreading aspect to the reaction.</para>
  
  <para>
    <figure><title>Model data</title>
      <screenshot>
        <graphic fileref="graphics/mousetrap-graphs.png"/>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    These two graphs show detail about the reaction rate. The top
    graph, the number of traps triggered over time, shows the
    classic result: the reaction initially spreads rapidly, but
    slows down and stops when it runs out of fuel (loaded
    mousetraps). The bottom graph is simply the number of events
    pending on the schedule, this corresponds to the number of ping
    pong balls currently in the air.</para>
  
</webpage>

<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document:("website.xml" "webpage")
End:
-->

