<partintro>  <title>Objectbase Introduction</title>

  <sidebar>    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> library encapsulates
      various fundamental aspects of the <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis>
      object model and defines the probing machinery used to take data
      from <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis> objects. Most of the underlying
      functionality of the classes defined here is contained in the
      <emphasis><link linkend="SWARM.DEFOBJ.SGML.REFERENCE">defobj</link></emphasis>
      and <emphasis><link linkend="SWARM.ACTIVITY.SGML.REFERENCE">activity</link></emphasis>
      libraries.
    </para>

  
    <formalpara><title>Probes</title> 
      
      <para>Probes are idealized entities that are intended to allow
        the user to monitor and modify the innards of objects without
        explicitly providing the functionality to do so at compile
        time. Hence, they allow dynamic interaction with an objects
        instance variables and methods. Most of the functionality of
        probes is implemented here; but, at present, they are
        intimately linked to the <emphasis><link linkend="SWARM.SIMTOOLSGUI.SGML.REFERENCE">simtools</link></emphasis>
        library, which contains all the widgetry needed to use probes
        from a GUI. Despite this intimacy, probes are intended to be a
        general purpose mechanism for <emphasis>any</emphasis> agent
        or device to interact dynamically with
        <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis> objects.  The Probes section in the
        &userbook; will explain more about the
        reasoning and purpose behind probes.
      </para>
    </formalpara>

  </sidebar>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Objectbase Dependencies" id="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.DEPEND">        <title>Dependencies</title> 

    <para>Following are the other header files imported by
    <filename>objectbase.h</filename>:

<programlisting>#import &lt;defobj.h&gt;
#import &lt;activity.h&gt;</programlisting>

      The <emphasis>defobj</emphasis> library interface is included to
      provide the basic object support. 
    </para>
<!-- Removed by AKL 1998-05-06
 
    The <EMPHASIS>SwarmObject</EMPHASIS> class header file was
    provided for backward compatibility since the
  <EMPHASIS>objectbase</EMPHASIS> library has been brought into
    agreement with the library standards.  
-->
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Objectbase Compatibility" id="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.COMPAT">        <title>Compatibility</title>

    <itemizedlist>      <listitem>        <formalpara><title>1.0.4 =&gt; 1.0.5</title>
          <para>No changes.</para></formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>        <formalpara><title>1.0.3 =&gt; 1.0.4</title>

          <para>The name of this library is now
            <emphasis><literal>objectbase</literal></emphasis>, it is has
            been renamed from
            <emphasis><literal>swarmobject</literal></emphasis> largely to
            reflect the more generic nature of the library and also
            motivated by the impending port of Swarm to Windows NT (to
            avoid filename conflicts with the
            <literal>SwarmObject</literal> class). There should be
            little, or no effect on the user, the only visible change
            is the fact that the actual library (.a) or (.so) file
            will now have a different name and the header file name
            has changed. A symbolic link from
            <literal>objectbase.h</literal> to
            <literal>swarmobject.h</literal> has been provided in the
            distribution, to ensure backwards compatibility, however,
            users should <emphasis>not</emphasis> continue to rely on
            this being so.  Users should port references to
            <literal>swarmobject.h</literal> in their code to
            <literal>objectbase.h</literal>, because this symlink will
            be removed in a future release.</para></formalpara>

        <para><emphasis><emphasis>Note</emphasis>: this is no way affects
          the</emphasis> <literal>SwarmObject</literal> class which
          remains the same as in all previous
          releases.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>        <formalpara>          <title>1.0.0 =&gt; 1.0.1</title>

          <para>The interface has changed again!
            <emphasis>EmptyProbeMap</emphasis> is now a subclass of
            <emphasis>CustomProbeMap</emphasis>, which is subclassed
            from <emphasis>ProbeMap</emphasis>. And a shortcut
            <literal>create:</literal> method was added to that
            branch.</para></formalpara>

        <para>Also, a new method was added to
          <emphasis>ProbeLibrary</emphasis> called
          <literal>isProbeMapDefinedFor</literal> that serves to
          non-invasively test for the existence of a
          <emphasis>ProbeMap</emphasis> for a given
          class.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem><formalpara>
          <title><emphasis>Beta</emphasis> =&gt; 1.0.0</title>

          <para>The new interface for the
            <emphasis>swarmobject</emphasis> library might cause some
            problems for apps that worked under the Beta release of
            Swarm. To get the whole scoop, read the <link linkend="SWARM.LIBRARY.SGML.APPENDIX">Library Interface
            Conventions</link>.

            <!-- To get a few hints at explicit changes you might need
            to make, check out: <LINK
            LINKEND="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.PORTINGAPPSTONEWINTERFACE.HTML">Porting
            apps to use the new <EMPHASIS>swarmobject</EMPHASIS>
            interface</LINK>.  -->

          </para>
        </formalpara>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Objectbase Usage Guide" id="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.USAGE">        <title>Usage Guide</title>

    <sect2>      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> library contains the
        most basic objects users need to design their agents and
        swarms.  It also serves, at present, as a repository for the
        probe machinery, which is provided for every
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>.  The way the classes in this
        library are to be used is varied.  But, basically, it is
        provided so that the user will have something to subclass from
        for her own objects and Swarms.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>      <title>Example Usage of <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis></title>

      <para>The best way to explain how the library should be used is
        to walk through an example.  So, using Heatbugs, we'll walk
        through the ways <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> is used and
        discuss them.  Since more documentation is usually better than
        less, I'm going to explain things at a low level so that those
        not familiar with Objective C will understand the discussion.
        If you already are familiar with Objective C, then you should
        skip this part.
      </para>

      <para>First off, the basic elements of the Heatbugs simulation
        are the heatbugs, the model swarm (which bundles the
        heatbugs), and the observer swarm (which bundles the displays
        of the probes poking into the model swarm and the heatbugs).
        The interface files for each show what must be imported and
        the declaration syntax needed to subclass from
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <para>We'll use <literal>Heatbug.h</literal> for our discussion
        here.  The first part of the file shows the C-preprocessor
        imports needed:

<programlisting>#import objectbase/SwarmObject.h
#import space.h			 
#import "HeatSpace.h"			 
#import tkobjc/Raster.h		 </programlisting>

      </para>

      <para>The <literal>#import objectbase/SwarmObject.h;</literal>
          is included in order to subclass from
          <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>.  However, to provide
          backwards compatibility, we've placed this import in the
          library interface file <literal>objectbase.h</literal> as
          well, which means one could subclass from
          <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis> by simply importing the
          <literal>objectbase.h</literal> file.  This is discouraged
          in order to make the library interfaces as standard as
          possible.
      </para>

      <para>The next <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> relevant piece of
      code in this file is:

<programlisting>@interface Heatbug: SwarmObject
{
  double unhappiness;		
  int x, y;			
  HeatValue idealTemperature;	
  HeatValue outputHeat;		
  float randomMoveProbability;	
  				
  Grid2d * world;		
  int worldXSize, worldYSize;	
  HeatSpace * heat;		
  Color bugColor;		
}</programlisting>

      </para>

      <para>The <literal>@interface</literal> keyword indicates that
        you are beginning the definition of the part of an object (a
        <emphasis>Heatbug</emphasis> in this case) that will be
        visible to other objects.  The <literal>Heatbug:
        SwarmObject</literal> indicates that you are calling this
        object <emphasis>Heatbug</emphasis> and it is a subclass of
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>.  What follows between the
        curly braces ({}) are the instance variables defined for the
        <emphasis>Heatbug</emphasis> class <emphasis>above and
        beyond</emphasis> those inherited from the
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis> class.
      </para>

      <para>Inside this "agent," we have defined several parameters
        associated with either the agent, itself, or the space in
        which it sits.  Any data that will need to be present
        throughout all the behavior and lifetime of the agent should
        be declared here.  Also, anything declared here will be
        accessible to the probe machinery, and so will be capable of
        being manipulated and viewed from outside the agent.
      </para>

      <para>Next come the message prototypes to which this agent will
        respond.  And it is worth noting again that these are
        <emphasis>in addition to</emphasis> those declared in the
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis> superclass.  So, not only
        will other objects be able to send messages to this agent that
        are declared here, but other objects will be able to send all
        the messages declared in the
        <literal>objectbase/SwarmObject.h</literal> imported
        previously.  The messages prototyped here will dictate what
        the compiler thinks this object can respond to.  Hence, if any
        part of any of these prototypes differs from the corresponding
        function definition in the <literal>Heatbug.m</literal> file,
        then the compiler will say something like <literal>Object:
        aHeatbug does not respond to xyz</literal>, where "xyz" is the
        name of the message that is being sent to the
        <literal>Heatbug</literal>.  A script is provided with the
        Swarm distribution that fixes header file prototypes to match
        the message declarations in the corresponding ".m" file.  This
        script should be in the <literal>$SWARMHOME/bin</literal>
        directory and is called <literal>m2h</literal>.
      </para>

      <para>One more thing to notice about these prototypes is that
        some of them are duplicates of what appears in the
        <literal>objectbase/SwarmObject.h</literal> file.  This means
        that when the message is called on a
        <emphasis>Heatbug</emphasis> object, it will execute the
        method defined here and not the one in the
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis> class.  In the
        <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> library, the following
        messages are intended to be overridden, as necessry:
        <literal>create:, createBegin:, createEnd, customizeBegin:,
        customizeEnd, customizeCopy:, describe:, and
        getInstanceName.</literal> Each of these messages do specific
        things that may change from subclass to subclass of
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>.  In this case, however,
        we're only overriding <literal>createEnd</literal>.  The
        differences between we implement it in
        <emphasis>Heatbugs</emphasis> and the default is not that
        significant.  But, it should be pointed out that when
        overriding certain messages, like
        <literal>createBegin:</literal> and
        <literal>createEnd</literal>, the new method should call the
        superclass' version of the message, as well.  This is done
        using the default pointer to the superclass, designated
        <emphasis>super</emphasis>.  The syntax in the
        <emphasis>Heatbugs</emphasis> case is:

<programlisting>[super createEnd];</programlisting>

      </para>

      <para>The reasons for doing this are related to the object phase
        protocols used by <emphasis>defobj</emphasis>.  If you would
        like more info on that, see the .
      </para>

      <para>Finally, the <literal>@end</literal> keyword signifies the
        end of the interface definition.  GNU Objective C allows one
        to leave this off; but, it is not good practice.</para>

      <para>And that's it.  Of course, there're a few tricky aspects
        to using the <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> library that
        weren't mentioned here.  Some of them will be mentioned in the
        <link linkend="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.ADVUSAGE">Advanced Usage
        Notes</link> and the <link linkend="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.IMPL">Implementation
        Notes</link>; but, the best way to learn is to examine the way
        the demo applications do it and try to make some changes
        yourself.</para>
    
    </sect2>

    <sect2>      <title>Subclassing from <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis></title>

      <para>Subclassing from the <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis> class
        works very similar to subclassing from
        <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>.
      </para>

      </sect2>
    
    <sect2>      <title>ActivityControl</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> object provides
        much more finely grained control over the execution of an
        interactive simulation.  It addresses both the problems of not
        being able to stop the simulation at any given point in any
        given activity and provides an initial step towards a Swarm
        debugger.
      </para>

      <para>An activity controller can be attached to
        <emphasis>any</emphasis> activity that is created in a Swarm
        simulation, including those that are created for use only by
        the Swarm kernel.  The controller then provides the basic
        activity manipulation messages on that activity, which are:
        <literal>run, stop, next, step, stepUntil,</literal> and
        <literal>terminate</literal>.
      </para>

      <para>The presence of the <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis>
        object might cause some confusion about what role the
        <emphasis>ControlPanel</emphasis> should play in the
        controlled execution of the various schedules.  The
        <emphasis>ControlPanel</emphasis> should still be used for the
        top-level control of any simulation that is running in a
        context where <emphasis>random</emphasis> interference is expected
        (like under a GUISwarm where the user may click a button at
        any time).  The reason this is true is because the
        <emphasis>ControlPanel</emphasis> sends pseudo-interrupts to
        the infinite loop we use to perpetuate execution of the top
        level Swarm (which can only be seen in the form of the
        <literal>go</literal> message on a
        <emphasis>GUISwarm</emphasis> at present).  <emphasis>This type
        of control may change in the future!</emphasis> But, for now, it
        is how we monitor the control state of the simulation.
      </para>

      <para>Now, having said that, the
        <emphasis>ControlPanel</emphasis> should no longer be used to
        run the simulation.  It should only be used to instantiate the
        control context and quit the entire simulation.  That means
        that sometime in the future, the <literal>Go</literal> and the
        <literal>Stop</literal> buttons will be removed from the
        <emphasis>ControlPanel</emphasis> display.  They have been
        left in for backwards compatibility so that applications that
        do not use the new <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> will
        retain their (albeit handicapped) controllability.  Also, the
        current <literal>Time Step</literal> button will be renamed to
        <literal>Start</literal> to be consistent with it's new
        purpose.
      </para>
      
      <para>In order to use the new control mechanism, you must place
        code like the following in the top-level Swarm.  (This code
        was taken from a modified mousetrap demo app.)
        
      </para>

<programlisting>observerActCont = [ActivityControl createBegin: [self getZone]];
observerActCont = [observerActCont createEnd];
[observerActCont attachToActivity: [self getSwarmActivity]];
[probeDisplayManager createProbeDisplayFor: observerActCont];</programlisting>

      <para>This creates an <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> and
        attaches it to the top-level activity (in this case an
        <literal>observerSwarm</literal>).  It also creates a display
        for the controller. (The probe map for the
        <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> class is designed within
        the <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis>, itself.  This is
        done because all of these objects are expected to look the
        same to any outside object.)  With this activity controller,
        you will then be able to <literal>run, stop, next, step,
        stepUntil,</literal> and <literal>terminate</literal> that
        activity.
      </para>

      <para>There are some tricky aspects to successfully using an
        <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> object that the <link linkend="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.ADVUSAGE"> Advanced Usage
        Notes</link> will cover.
      </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Objectbase Advanced Usage Guide" id="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.ADVUSAGE">        <title>Advanced Usage Guide</title>

    <sect2>      <title>ProbeMap design</title>

      <para>When designing a <emphasis>ProbeMap</emphasis> for a given
        (subclass of) <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>, inclusion of
        instance variables or messages defined in the super class
        might be desirable.  The normal <emphasis>ProbeMap</emphasis>
        design code might look like (this code was taken from the
        tutorial app called "hello-world"):
      </para>

<programlisting>probeMap = [CustomProbeMap createBegin: [self getZone]];
[probeMap setProbedClass: [person class]];
probeMap = [probeMap createEnd];
[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "room"
  				 inClass: [person class]]];
[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "party"
  				 inClass: [person class]]];
[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "name"
  				 inClass: [person class]]];
[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "stillhere"
  				 inClass: [person class]]];
[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "listOfFriends"
  				 inClass: [person class]]];
[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "myColor"
  				 inClass: [person class]]];
[probeLibrary setProbeMap: probeMap For: [person class]];
[probeDisplayManager createProbeDisplayFor: person];</programlisting>

      <para>where <literal>room, party, name, stillhere,
          listOfFriends,</literal> and <literal>myColor</literal> are
          instance variables declared in the interface to the
          <emphasis>Person</emphasis> subclass.  And
          <emphasis>Person</emphasis> is a subclass of
          <emphasis>Agent2d</emphasis>, which is a subclass of
          <emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <para>Now let's say that there are two variables declared in
        <emphasis>Agent2d</emphasis> that you want to put into this
        custom probe in addition to the ones you've picked out of
        <emphasis>Person</emphasis>.  Call them <literal>x</literal>
        and <literal>y</literal>.  The way to add them to the
        <literal>probeMap</literal> is to add the following two lines
        of code to the above.
      </para>

<programlisting>[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "x"
  				 inClass: [Agent2d class]]];
[probeMap addProbe: [probeLibrary getProbeForVariable: "y"
					 inClass: [Agent2d class]]];</programlisting>

      <para>And that's it!  The two superclass-declared variables,
        which are, in fact, instance variables of the instance of the
        subclass, are now included in the probe.
      </para>

      <para>In addition, a convenience message has been added to the
        <emphasis>CustomProbeMap</emphasis> interface to compress the
        above rather cluttered mechanism into one message.  This
        convenience message can be used in the usual case where a
        <emphasis>ProbeMap</emphasis> will consist of variables and
        messages from the same class.  For example, the first part of
        the custom probe creation above can be shortened to:

<programlisting>probeMap = [CustomProbeMap create: [self getZone] forClass: [person class]
      withIdentifiers: "room", "party", "name", "stillhere",
                       "listOfFriends", "myColor", NULL];</programlisting>

        And if the user wanted messages in the probe as well, it could
        be extended to:

<programlisting>probeMap = [CustomProbeMap create: [self getZone] 
                          forClass: [person class]
                   withIdentifiers: "room", "party", "name",
                       "stillhere", "listOfFriends", "myColor", 
                       ":",
                       "setWorld:Room:Party:",
                       "setPerson:Topic_array:ShowSpeech:",
                       NULL];</programlisting>

      </para>

      <para>At present, this message doesn't search the superclasses
        for the message names listed here.  But, that will soon be
        rectified.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>      <title>ActivityControl Issues</title>

      <para> It is completely reasonable to assume that explicit
        control can be had over all the activities in a simulation.
        However, at present, this control is limited because the
        context in which an activity runs determines how it behaves.
        To understand how an <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> is
        to be used, we will have to explore the behavior of activities
        in context.  (For a more complete explanation of the behavior
        of activities, see the <emphasis><link linkend="SWARM.ACTIVITY.SGML.REFERENCE">activity
        library</link></emphasis> documentation.)
      </para>

      <para>There are two ways to get an activity started, one can
        activate the activity in <literal>nil</literal> or in some
        other activity.  So called "top-level" activities are
        activated in <literal>nil</literal> and are intended to be
        independent of the sophisticated scheduling activity that
        dictates the execution of actions in any other context in the
        simulation.  I.e. the only activities that should be activated
        in <literal>nil</literal> are those sets of events that are
        expected to preserve the same behavior no matter what goes on
        in any other part of the simulation.
      </para>

      <para>The other type of activity, those activated in some other
        activity, is intended to be an integral part of its owner
        activity.  However, this doesn't mean that it
        <emphasis>must</emphasis> depend on the outcome of actions
        happening in the owner activity.  In fact, an
        <emphasis>ActionPlan</emphasis> can be designated as
        containing actions that are capable of being processed in
        parallel, via code like the following:


<programlisting>[anActionPlan setDefaultOrder: Concurrent];</programlisting>

        But these activities are <emphasis>still</emphasis> intended to be
        meshed with their owner activities.  In other words, they are
        part and parcel of the same model or simulation.</para>

      <para>Now, the operational effect of activating an activity in
        <literal>nil</literal> is that it will not be meshed with the
        rest of the Swarm activity structure.  This gives the user (or
        process) complete control over the execution of that activity.
        A <literal>run</literal> on that activity will run either to
        completion or until a stop flag is set by a sequence of events
        purely internal to that activity.  Or, one can stop it from
        the outside with a message from something like an
        <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis>.
      </para>
      
      <para>What all this means is that, while one can attach an
        <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> to <emphasis>any</emphasis>
        activity, only the "top-level" activities (those having been
        activated in <literal>nil</literal>) are going to respond well
        to it.  Any sub-activity will respond half-heartedly, if at
        all.  For example, in the <emphasis>Mousetrap</emphasis> demo
        distributed with Swarm, an
        <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> has been placed on both
        the <emphasis>ObserverSwarm</emphasis> and the
        <emphasis>ModelSwarm</emphasis> activities.  Now, if one sends
        a <literal>run</literal> message to the
        <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> that is attached to the
        <literal>observerSwarm</literal>'s activity, the entire model
        continues to run to completion, unless the user sends a
        <literal>stop</literal> message.  However, if the sim is
        stopped at some point, a <literal>run</literal> message to the
        <literal>modelSwarm</literal>'s activity will have no effect
        at all.  (<emphasis>Note:</emphasis> If you do this via the
        activity controllers, you see the
        <literal>currentTime</literal> variable get updated; but, the
        actual <literal>run</literal> message to the activity, itself,
        has no effect.)
      </para>

      <para>So, the rule of thumb, for the present, is to attach
        <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> objects only to
        "top-level" activities, like the
        <emphasis>ObserverSwarm</emphasis>.
      </para>

    </sect2>


  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Objectbase Subclassing Reference" id="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.SUBCLASS">        <title>Subclassing Reference</title>

    <para>The main classes defined here that are intended to be
      subclassed by users are Swarm and SwarmObject. The probing
      functionality provided here is mainly for use within the
      <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis> kernel. However, this probe machinery
      should be used when designing any interface between
      <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis> and any other agent or
      device. </para>

    <formalpara><title>SwarmObject</title>
      <para><emphasis>SwarmObject</emphasis> is the base class for all
      interactive agents in <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis>.  It defines
      the standard behavior for Swarmstyle agents, which includes
      hooks for creation, probing, zoned memory allocation, and
      destruction.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara><title>Swarm</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis> class encapsulates all of
      the abstract execution machinery in the
      <emphasis>activity</emphasis> library, as well as the notion of
      a group of related objects. Metaphorically, a "Swarm" is a
      combination of a collection of objects and a schedule of
      activity over those objects. Hence, the
      <emphasis>Swarm</emphasis> class provides the behavior necessary
      for creating such an object and starting up the schedule.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <para>Further details on subclassing are also described in the
      <link linkend="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.USAGE">Usage
      Guide</link></para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Objectbase Interface Design Notes" id="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.DESIGN">        <title>Interface Design Notes</title>

    <para>Unfortunately, this interface has not undergone a rigorous
      design review.  As such it is subject to change in the future.
      However, there are rumours that this library will be integrated
      into the <emphasis><link linkend="SWARM.DEFOBJ.SGML.REFERENCE">defobj
      library</link></emphasis> anyway.  So, even though little
      thought was given to the design of this interface (and it is not
      likely to be worthwhile designing a robust interface at this
      time), it was implemented in order to provide a first step
      towards bringing all the various libraries in line with the
      standard set by <emphasis>defobj</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Along these lines, a few notes are relevant.
    
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>          <para><emphasis>Probe</emphasis>s may become an inherent
          part of any object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>          <para><emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis>s will become a
            part of a larger set of tools used for debugging Swarm
            models. </para>
        </listitem>
<!--  Removed by AKL 1998-05-06
 
      <LISTITEM>
      <PARA>The explicit importation of the
      <EMPHASIS>SwarmObject</EMPHASIS> interface should be
        removed.  This is only provided for backward compatibility
        and when all the libraries follow the interface
        conventions, then those conventions should be
        encouraged.</PARA>
      </listitem>
-->

      </orderedlist>
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xreflabel="Objectbase Implementation Notes" id="SWARM.OBJECTBASE.SGML.SECT1.IMPL">        <title>Implementation Notes</title>

    <orderedlist>      
      <listitem>        <para>Right now, <emphasis>Probe</emphasis>'s rely on a
          special method, <literal>getInstanceName</literal>, that has
          to be implemented in any probe-able object in order to get
          anything other than the class name of that object into the
          object designation widget.  However, a more general
          capability has been added to <emphasis>defobj</emphasis> to
          give a meaningful name to any object.
          <emphasis>Probe</emphasis>s will be changed to take
          advantage of this new capability.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>        <para>In the <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> the
          frequency of the message <literal>updateStateVar</literal>
          is very high.  It is sent at least once every cycle and
          <emphasis>every</emphasis> time a message is sent to the
          <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis>.  This is
          unsatisfactory.  Some of these messages can be pruned out of
          the object.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>        <para>The <literal>probeMap</literal> designed for use with an
          <emphasis>ActivityControl</emphasis> was chosen fairly
          arbitrarily.  Right now, it serves as a default for the
          class.  A user can override it by designing a new one and
          inserting it into the <literal>probeLibrary</literal>.
          </para></listitem>

      <listitem>        <para>Errors specific to objects in the
          <emphasis>objectbase</emphasis> library need to be gathered
          and initialized like those in the
          <emphasis>defobj</emphasis> library.</para>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

  </sect1>
</partintro><!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document:("objectbasecont.sgml" "PARTINTRO")
End:
-->
